Now, this is beautiful, no?
Camille Pissarro,
dean of the impressionists.
Notice how he's abandoned precision
in favor of expression, how alive it all is.
What about this?
Well, that, I'm afraid, is not for sale.
It's entirely too valuable.
Right, Silvia?
Watch out!
Go, go!
- Back! Up against the desk!
- What are you doing?!
- I said move!
- 60 seconds!
- Pick it up! Let's go!
- Let's go!
- Stay back, Silvia.
- Come on! Clock is running!
Come on! Move!
Go, go, go! Move!
Take it!
Go! Come on!
Pick up your feet!
No, no, no,
don't you touch that!
- Don't be stupid.
- Time is running!
I'm telling you,
that's worth nothing to you.
- Take it.
- John, no. John, don't!
- We're good!
- Let's go! Let's go! Let's go!
Somebody help me!
Go, go, go!
What's all this?
Oh, well,
that's the art squad.
They deal with stolen art
and stuff like that.
Yeah, their offices on the sixth
floor are being remodeled
so I told them to set up in the conference
room for the time being.
Mrs. Hennigan, why was your husband
trying to save this painting in particular?
That's me.
John painted it years ago,
when we first met.
We fell in love
as he was painting it.
It's not worth any money,
but it was worth a lot to us.
To me.
We'll do our best
to get it back for you.
This gang
that did this, uh...
We've been chasing them
for quite a while now.
They're really good
at what they do.
I can't believe he's gone.
Well, he's not gone.
He's alive as long as you're alive
to remember him. He lives in you.
It's a cliché. I know.
But it's true.
I'm special agent Marcus Pike.
This is agent Searls.
You're Patrick Jane, right?
Abbott's guy.
- Well, he's my guy.
- Thanks for sharing your floor with us.
You people need some help, huh?
- What makes you say that?
- His shoulders.
- Hey, now, uh...
- Hey, now, I'm just saying
if you need some help,
I could help you.
- I mean, murder is my business.
- Sure.
I've heard good things about you.
We'd be happy to have your input.
These guys, they're...
They're really good and our cases
don't usually lead to homicide.
But you are going to
catch them, aren't you?
I hate to sound immodest, ma'am,
but, uh, I rarely fail.
Patrick.
- Sylvia.
- Welcome to the fishbowl.
You volunteered us
to handle the case?
I decide what cases
we take next.
Well, I was just being neighborly
and the art squad seemed all for it.
Well, of course they were.
They've been chasing this group
for years, with no luck.
And what do you know
about catching art thieves?
Nothing at all.
That's why it'll be fun.
Okay. We'll take it.
Get a hold of agent Pike
in the art squad.
Get up to speed
on this thing.
Let's show 'em how it's done.
This is special agent Marcus Pike
from the art-theft squad.
He's being attached to our team
while we work the case.
Uh, I've asked him
to get you guys up to speed.
Art thieves used to be
about sneaking...
Nighttime break-ins.
Not anymore...
the new generation prefers guns.
This guy is the leader.
He does the talking, runs the show.
But until yesterday morning,
he's never killed anybody.
They've done about six jobs between
Dallas and Phoenix in the last two years
taken down about $100 million
worth in art and artifacts.
We're in the wrong business.
Stolen art can take
a long time to sell
so our guess is that they're
sitting on a lot of the art
including the paintings
from yesterday's heist.
If we have those paintings we can
nail them for John Hennigan's murder
so it's imperative
that we find this art stash.
They must have left us
something to work with.
Well, they've only
slipped up once.
We found a glove a few blocks
from a gallery they robbed in phoenix.
We managed to get a partial
print, and we got a hit.
Aaron Pulaski... time for
armed robbery and battery.
He's also the former middleweight
boxing champ at Folsom prison.
And you can't charge a man
for owning a glove.
Yeah, we brought him in for questioning
but he lawyered up quick and told us zip.
- These guys are pros.
- If he's a known felon
we should have his known associates
hangouts, stuff like that.
We do, but nothing's popped.
He doesn't seem to have a lot of friends.
He hangs out a lot at a bar on 6th street.
- We could set a tail on him.
- Eh, could be waiting for weeks.
My plan is a little more elaborate
but it's much more entertaining.
- Of course it is.
- You already have a plan?
Well, as you know, agent Lisbon,
the key to a good con
is always making the mark
feel that he is in control.
I mean, you can lead a man anywhere
as long as he thinks that he is driving.
So, how do we do that?
Well, first, we rope him in
with some flash
then we steer them towards
a couple of good inside men a face.
We're gonna need some art for the gaff
and then a good false blow-off.
- I don't know what any of that means.
- You'll get used to it.
- But if you want art, I got art.
- Good.
I always feel a little bit
like Aladdin right here.
Okay. Now we're having fun.
Where does all this stuff
come from?
- It's stolen.
- What do you mean?
Sometimes we get
just part of a haul
and we sit on the art so the
crooks don't know have a lead
and we keep it here while
we investigate the rest of it.
And nobody knows
about it?
Well, we keep a pretty tight
lid, our own secret museum.
Impressive.
You bring dates here?
No. Just... Once or twice.
Fantastic. Gorgeous.
I love you, agent Pike.
Everything we need.
I'm gonna make you a list.
We should be ready to roll in about a week.
Well, I... I don't want to
second-guess you, Mr. Jane
but if you want to use
these paintings as bait
the guy running this crew
knows a lot about art.
- He'll know this stuff is stolen.
- Yes. That's the point.
- Good morning.
So, what's the plan
to catch these art thieves?
Well, I am just as curious
as you are.
Jane has been playing this real close
to his chest until he figures it out.
He said he'll be here
to brief us any moment.
You sure about that?
Morning.
Where's Jane?
- Still at the party house.
- The party house?
- Wait till you see it.
- Uh, w... this is his idea.
How are we supposed to know what to do
if he's not here to tell us?
He gave me notes.
Okay, very well.
Please brief the team, agent Wylie.
Okay.
Here we go.
We want the leader of the gang,
the one who shot John Hennigan.
To find him, we need to gain
the trust of Pulaski.
So, we know he likes to spend time
at the favorite bar.
That's where we rope him. We need
to plant some bugs and cameras in the bar.
- Why?
- So I can monitor it from here.
You're our roper.
Jane said you'd know about boxing.
Well, I never told him,
but, yes, I do.
So does Pulaski.
That's a good place to start.
I've got some tips for you,
if you, uh...
But you... you probably know
what you're doing.
You're the muscle. Jane said
that you could handle your own wardrobe.
Yeah, I can do that.
Jane said that the two of you
could work out the choreography.
Oh, yeah. That's easy.
Lisbon is playing the
inside man... woman...
Inside woman, with Jane.
He wants you to wear this.
- Yowza.
- It's a bit much, isn't it?
This is for you.
You're the face.
Once Pulaski is at the party,
you lure him into the bedroom.
Jane's got some ideas.
Yeah. Thanks.
I think I've got it under control.
Then Jane and Lisbon
Take over.
And then what happens?
"And then the fun really starts."
That's a direct quote.
Hey. Lone star.
- We ready?
- Yeah. It just started.
God...
My man.
Hey, let me get
some of those.
That's a nice
opening gambit.
- Well, how's that?
- You see what he did there?
He asked him
for some napkins. So?
Jane told me about this.
You want someone to trust you,
you don't give them something.
You get them to give you something,
even something small.
It'll make them think they've invested
in you. It's all subconscious.
Hey, my man, y'all showing
the Reynoso fight tomorrow?
Oh, that's what's up. Okay.
Whoo, baby.
My bookie is gonna be
weeping about that.
Reynoso is going down. You know,
that kid is a little bit too fast for him.
Don't waste your money, bro.
Kid's got speed, but he's got
no power and no chin.
You think so, huh?
Yeah.
Look at these two.
There's absolutely no commitment.
We're getting close.
Now he just needs to move
that arm, and we're all good.
It's guarding behavior.
Jane told me to watch for it.
He moves that arm, it means
he's comfortable with Abbott.
- Maybe he's not gonna do it.
- No, he's gonna do it. Watch.
- There you go.
- Cool.
I'll let Jane know
the mark has been roped.
- Okay.
- All right.
- All right, let me finish.
- Yeah, all right.
Okay, so...
so, I've got him.
I got him up against the ropes,
and I... bam! Pop him in the liver.
The sucker folds in half
like a deck chair.
- It was perfect.
- There's nothing like a liver shot
to make a grown man
call for his mama.
- Ain't that the truth?
- Right?
- You want another shot?
- Hey, line 'em up, man.
Two.
That was perfect.
Absolutely.
Perfect. Oh, man.
That is perfect.
- Oh, man.
- Look at these guys!
You have an annoying laugh.
What's that?
A loud, annoying laugh.
You made me miss my shot.
Hey, man, you miss, you lose.
Live with it.
- Don't touch the money!
- Hey, brother, take my advice.
Get out of my face
and go back to your game.
I'm not your brother.
And what are you looking at?
Whoa! Hey, hey!
- What's wrong with you, man?
- Yeah man.
He's got a gun!
Yeah, you better run.
- That dude is crazy!
- Yeah, you got that right.
My laugh is not annoying.
Well, I guess we have to find
another place to drink.
This yours?
Yeah. Why?
You need a lift?
- Yeah.
- All right. Come on.
Thanks.
Whew! We're here.
- This is our new drinking place?
- Yeah. It's my boss's house.
Swag.
If you don't mind me asking
what line of business you in?
Whatever needs doing.
- Hey!
- Dennis, you wicked man.
Where have you been?
And who is this handsome brute?
Teresa, this is my friend Aaron.
Fabulous to meet you, Aaron.
Any friend of Dennis. Come on in.
Dennis, you old rascal.
I am so glad you came.
And who do we have here?
- This is my friend Aaron.
- Aaron, pleasure to meet you.
- Pisces?
- No. Sagittarius.
Close, but no cigar.
I like you anyway.
And you can relax
make yourself at home, grab a drink.
Oh, isn't he fabulous?
Such a mean face.
- Yeah. There it is.
- Down, girl.
You're doing very well.
Just a little, uh... a little big.
- Big? Really?
- Yeah, try a little less Joan Crawford
- And a little more Barbara Stanwyck.
- How do you know what that means?
Look, I can't walk,
and you're giving me acting tips?
- Just stay upright. Keep smiling.
- I can't breathe in this dress.
Can you pass the rice, please?
Where did the house
come from?
It's a drug forfeiture,
on loan from the D.E.A.
so, what's the story
with Jane and Lisbon?
She was working for the California
bureau of investigation in Sacramento
- and then his wife and child were...
- No, I mean, are they in a relationship?
- A couple?
- No, no.
I used to think so,
but they're not.
I don't think.
- How's it going?
- It's going good.
- You got a nice right cross.
- Thanks.
We just ate. There's some
vindaloo left, I think, if you want.
No, I'm good.
So, Abbott roped the mark,
got him to the party.
He's met the inside man...
Jane, that is.
Now we're just waiting on the face
to lure the mark to the bedroom.
- Has he been talking like this all night?
- Yeah.
Ah, here we go.
Hey, now.
"Hey, now," yourself.
- What's your name, sweetheart?
- Kim.
Aaron.
You are smoking hot.
You're like a damn fire hazard
walking around here.
- Oh, hush.
- No, for real.
The eagle has landed.
We only just met.
Oh, I feel like we've known
each other so long.
Perhaps we hooked up
in a previous life.
Oh... You mean like you were
Napoleon and I was Josephine?
I was thinking more like Mickey Rourke
and Kim Basinger, you know what I'm saying?
You are a very naughty boy.
Whoa, whoa.
Slow down there, cowboy.
What's the matter, baby?
Come here.
When I said,
"make yourselves at home"
that's not exactly what I meant.
That's... that's my bed.
I'm sorry, man.
You see a chance like this, you take it.
Kim, really?
You have no self-control. Out.
Sorry, boss.
Anything that moves.
What the hell?
Is that a Van Gogh?
I'd never have pegged you
as an art lover.
It's a fake.
- All of it?
- Yeah, afraid so.
I couldn't afford them
if they were real.
What is it that you do?
I mean for money?
- Software.
- Software?
Haven't seen a computer
in your whole house.
Never take your work home with you.
Key to a happy life.
Let's go downstairs,
have some fun.
Hey. It's Pulaski.
I think I've found something.
Nope. You're gonna
want to see this yourself.
Thanks for the party.
I had a great time.
You get her home safe.
I can take her home.
Maybe in the next life.
Right.
Looks like your ride ditched you.
- Can I call you a car?
- No, I'm good.
- Thanks for the party.
- My pleasure.
Patrick? Are you up there?
Everybody's gone.
"I'm sorry. The party's over."
"Where did you get this painting?"
"My boyfriend will know.
He's on his way up."
All right, fellas,
what's the situation?
Well, Pulaski left a sliding door open
before he left and this guy came through it.
- We got a name?
- I'm working on it.
Oh, I keep finding strangers
in my bedroom.
Guess it was a good party.
- You all right, Teresa?
- I am now that you're here.
- He wants to know about the painting.
- It's a fake.
No, it isn't. It's the real Mccoy.
It was stolen two years ago.
- Really?
- Yeah. So...
What's the deal?
Uh... I don't know that we've met.
I'm... I'm Patrick.
- And this is Teresa.
- Hi.
MacKaye.
I'll cross-reference the name
"MacKaye" with the picture.
Edwin MacKaye, a Dallas
resident, business owner.
He owns some local restaurants
Fast-food joints, that kind of thing.
Cash business... that's good
for money laundering.
- Criminal record?
- No. He's clean. Ex-military.
Oh, and look...
a minor in art history.
Oh, that's our boy.
If Jane's theory is right
then he should be
the leader of the gang
which means he's the one
that killed Hennigan.
Okay, cut the cute stuff.
You stole these.
It's what you do.
I mean, these are all stolen.
How do you know so much about it?
Are you a cop?
Oh, don't you get it?
- This gentleman's one of us.
- He doesn't look like one of us.
No. He's a heavy, a shooter.
I'm direct.
And you're one of those grifter types, huh?
You, uh, prefer tricks?
You could say that.
Eh. Never saw a trick
that could beat a bullet.
Well, it's always nice to get tips
from the competition.
Oh, I-I don't have competition.
See, Texas is my territory.
You've got to go someplace else.
I hear Miami's hot.
Are you saying this town
ain't big enough for the two of us?
Yeah.
I'm not playing with you.
Oh, I get it.
But I think you're a businessman.
Now, you can try to run us
out of town
or maybe you can stop and think
about what brought us to town.
- You got a job planned?
- A big one.
- The Vermeer at the DMA?
- Lousy escape routes.
- The hirst sculpture?
- Too heavy.
- Violets.
- Give the man a cigar. He's a sharp one.
Well, I guess you've got
three options.
You can cut me in on the job
you can get out of town tonight
or I just hurt the two of you badly.
What do you think?
You know, you should have
been a salesman.
What do you say darling?
Are we gonna cut this thug in on our plan?
It's better than him
hurting us badly.
Welcome to the team.
- This is Pike.
- "Hey. It's Lisbon."
I'm just checking in
before I go to bed.
"Okay, well, we, uh...
we shut down the inside cameras"
so you don't have to worry about
any more prying eyes.
And, just so you know,
there is someone outside the house.
We're guessing it's another one
of MacKaye's crew.
Well, that's gonna
make me sleep better.
"No, we've got eyes on him.
Don't worry."
You're safe.
I wouldn't lie to you.
That's a nice
change of pace.
I feel like everything
I've done today is a lie.
Well, you were, uh...
you were real good.
"I learned from the best."
I'm starving, and there's nothing
to eat in this house.
Well, that's a shame.
There's a pretty good diner
just down the street from you...
Biscuits and gravy,
if that's your thing.
- Not really.
- All right, well, what about pancakes?
I could go for some pancakes.
They have about six kinds...
chocolate chip, banana
- "All that good stuff."
- Now you're just trying to torture me.
Maybe. Just a little bit.
I could have some sent over to you.
You said there's a guy
watching the house, remember?
Yeah, you're right. I won't tease you
anymore. I won't even mention the waffles.
I'm gonna go downstairs and see
if there's some canapés left from the party.
All right, well, I don't know
what a canapé is. But bon appétit.
- Good night, Lisbon.
- Good night.
Fischer.
Good job on getting Pulaski
to the bedroom.
Candy from a baby.
How did we do?
This guy paid Jane and Lisbon a visit
after the party was over... Edwin MacKaye.
Looks like he's the one
who killed Hennigan.
So what's our next move?
Jane's plan's working so far,
so we stick with it.
Yeah. I want you to handle the takedown.
It's gonna be dangerous.
- You got it.
- All right.
Fischer, I want you
to handle the streets.
Jane gave us a list of things
that he needs.
A marching band?
- Yeah. A marching band.
- Yes, sir.
Well, you just love
popping up places, don't you?
- Let's go.
- And good morning to you, too.
Shotgun.
"Manet painted it as
a gift for his brother's wife."
His forbidden love.
He couldn't express
his love to her in words
so he did it a different way...
with a painting.
It's worth maybe $100 million
if it ever went to auction.
- You have someone who wants it?
- We've got a customer lined up.
- How much?
- $5 million.
50/50 split.
Fair enough.
Now, you've probably got some
cute, little plan to get us in and out
no fuss, no muss, huh?
Well, I do like to keep
my muss to a minimum.
I don't do cute.
Tricks, cleverness...
it's a waste of time.
- You'd be surprised.
- Ah, fast and simple.
"That's the way to do things."
"And you're the one
behind the wheel."
This is the part I don't understand.
We're not gonna rob the museum.
- No.
- Why not?
I mean, he robs the painting
from the museum
we catch him red-handed,
case closed, we all go home.
But then we wouldn't be able to prove
that he murdered John Hennigan.
Besides, Jane said that MacKaye
doesn't want to rob the museum.
Then why is he at the museum
with Jane?
'Cause he wants to get Jane
and Lisbon out of the house.
That's okay, 'cause we know
what they're gonna do next.
Well, damn.
- So, they hid all the paintings.
- Yep.
Thinks he's smart.
Thinks he's pulling one
over on me.
So, what do we do?
We hit them... the old-fashioned
way, hard and fast.
I figure four minutes.
We get in, we open the safe, we get out.
And what if this Patrick guy stalls
in giving us the combinations?
He acts like he doesn't care
about anything
but I see the way
he looks at his girlfriend.
See, that...
that's the soft spot.
He gives us any trouble
I shoot the brunette in the head.
We need to keep at least one of them alive
until we get the safe open.
After that, if one of them gets in the way
it's open season.
- Up, now!
- Whoa, sorry. Didn't hear the doorbell.
No talking.
To the bedroom... now.
Stay with her.
If I give the word, kill her.
- Let's go!
- I'll be back in two shakes, babe.
- Move.
- Oh, so demanding.
Would you like a drink?
We have some champagne right here.
Don't say a word.
Drop the gun now.
Open the safe.
Oh, you know about the safe.
That's a depressing development.
- Faster!
- Yeah, slow and steady opens the safe.
Voilà.
Here.
- Hold on.
- What?
I don't like the look on his face.
Tracking device, yeah?
You think I'm stupid?
Ask me that question again
when you don't have a gun.
Okay.
You stay up here for a full minute
after we're gone.
- You understand?
- Yep.
One, Mississippi...
Shouldn't have come back, fellas.
Now, why don't you put the guns down
so we can discuss it?
Bastard.
He's in the back!
Hey! What you're doin'?
Hey!
Okay.
2235 Fritz street, off Singleton.
Yes, sir.
- Keep the change.
- Thanks. Have a nice day.
FBI! Put your hands
on your head!
Do it now!
All right.
Let's be very clear
about something.
We don't need you
to say anything.
We already have the rest
of your crew in custody.
We have FBI witnesses
for armed robbery
assault, kidnapping.
We have enough stolen art
to start a museum.
And, best of all
we have the paintings
that prove you killed John Hennigan.
- Lawyer.
Well, um, that is your right.
Oh, what song was the marching
band playing, by the way?
The marching band that,
blocked off the alleyway.
- What song were they playing?
- What are you talking about?
Well, I requested
"the yellow rose of Texas."
Were they playing
"the yellow rose of Texas"?
The garbage truck, the marching
band... you did all that?
You steered me to the cab, huh?
The illusion of control.
It made you feel safe enough to go
where you kept the paintings.
Now, unless you have
any further questions
about how I played you
like a big, old bassoon
I have someplace...
Fabulous to go.
Au revoir.
What's this?
It's case-closed pizza. It's an old
tradition. Thought I'd bring it back.
- Next time, it's on me.
- Deal.
- How is it?
- It's all right.
You probably like that
Chicago-style stuff, right?
Pizza's pizza.
I'm not really
in the mood for pizza.
You know what sounds good?
Those pancakes we were talking about before.
- Those did sound good.
- Do you want to go?
- Right now?
- Yeah.
Dinner is the best time
for breakfast.
What do you say?
That's really sweet, but...
look, if you don't want to go, just say so.
We're cool. It's good.
But I like you and I think you're a hell
of a good-looking woman
and I'd love
to get to know you better.
- Let's do it.
- Let's go.
All right.
Excuse me.
I was told to come here.
Oh, yes. Please, come in.
Is it true you got the man
who killed john?
Yes, I did, and I also got this.
Don't... don't they need it
for the trial?
Oh, no. Don't worry about that.
It's true what you said.
He's...
He's still here.
Okay, so, where are we going?
Um... well... uh, y...
Oh, no, no. You... you kids
go ahead and have fun.
- Good night, Jane.
- Good night.
Okay.
Have fun.